גוט טוב, Gut tov, today's דף daf is נג, nun gimmel, 53,
and we are in the middle of a discussion.
We're moving on to the part of the משנה mishnah that focuses
on the skull and the backbone. And the first thing to establish
was whether it only was the two of them combined that are
מטמא באוהל metameh b'ohel or each alone. All the evidence pointed to
each alone and that's the way the רמבם Rambam rules. And now
the next question is, let's say you don't have the whole skull
and backbone, but you have enough of a quantity of them. We've
already learned that if you have a quarter of a קב kav
of רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין, rov binyan, it causes
טומאה באוהל tuma b'ohel and double that, a half of a קב,
kav, is נזיר מגלח. Nazir migaleach. The נזיר Nazir would have to
shave his head and reverse the whole thing. So that's these are
the two sort of cases where we have a different amount for
the נזיר Nazir to shave as opposed to what causes טומאה באוהל.
tuma b'ohel. And the assumption is, is that the same way that's
a quantity drawn from רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין, rov
binyan, similarly a quantity of a רביעית קב revi'it kav drawn from
שדרה וגולגולת shidra v'gulgollet even if you don't have their entirety which
cause טומאת אוהל tumas b'ohel and half a קב kav would have
would be for נזיר מגלח. Nazir migaleach. The question that was put
out there, that's sort of like the assumption, the question that was
put out there by רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama was that
since שדרה וגולגולת shidra v'gulgollet are much weightier, you know, that there's
just two bones and they represent the whole body, there was even
and actually even each one of them alone represents the whole body
the way we פסקן pasken either the שדרה shidra or the גולגולת.
gulgollet. So since they're so sort of representative and weighty and so
on, perhaps even a smaller quantity of them should be נזיר מגלח.
Nazir migaleach. Maybe for the נזיר מגלח Nazir migaleach you don't need
a half of a קב, kav, maybe a רביעית קב revi'it kav
would be enough, the same amount that normally causes טומאה. tuma. Okay,
so that's the question that we're in the middle of, we have
one more proof to that, so let's take a look. Top of
נג, nun gimmel, עמוד א, amud aleph, three lines from the top.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. שמאי אומר, Shammai omer, עצם
אחד מן השדרה ומן הגולגולת. etzem echad min hashidra u'min hagulgollet. So
we had this before that שמאי Shammai says even one bone
from the backbone or from the skull causes this טומאה tuma and
טומאה tuma that a נזיר Nazir would shave over. So let's try
to extrapolate from בית שמאי Beit Shammai what the other opinion is.
We did this before and in the end we're going to say
you can't exactly figure out what the other opinion is based on
שמאי. Shammai. But let's take a look. So you see, so implicitly
if שמאי Shammai says even one bone from them,
the opposing opinion presumably would say nevertheless a small quantity would be
enough, a רביעית קב revi'it kav should suffice. So the גמרא Gemara
obviously says you can't figure out from שמאי Shammai what the opposite
opinion is. שאני שמאי דמחמיר טפי, shani Shammai d'machmir tfei, שמאי Shammai
is very strict. The opposing opinion might say, number one, you need
a whole skull and a whole backbone that we know and they
might say if you have a certain quantity of it, maybe you
need a half קב. kav. Just because שמאי Shammai is so strict
in one direction doesn't mean that the other school agrees to that
great strictness of שמאי Shammai and they might say it's the normal
rule of a half קב. kav. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לפשוט מינה, lifshot minah, so then
fine, let's try to assume your way that it that they go
to the opposite direction. טעמא דשמאי דמחמיר, tama d'Shammai d'machmir,
שמאי Shammai is very strict, הא רבנן, ha rabanan, so presumably the
position that argues on שמאי Shammai would be the most sort of
lenient, has no strictness,
and would say עד חצי קב עצמות ad chatzi kav atzamot and
would say you
need a half קב. kav. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא
עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דשמאי אלא בעצם אחד אבל ברוב
עצמות רביעית קב אפילו רבנן מודי. dilma ad kan lo pligi rabanan
alei d'shammai ela b'etzem echad aval b'rov atzamot revi'it kav afilu rabanan
modei.
How do you know? Doesn't mean just the point is we don't
know what the other opinion is. They just disagree with שמאי Shammai
that one bone is not enough. אבל ברוב עצמות, aval b'rov atzamot,
but a quarter of a קב kav of עצמות, atzamot, אפילו רבנן
מודי, afilu rabanan modei, maybe they might agree. So it's the same
thing we said before in a different discussion which is, which is
just from שמאי Shammai you can't infer what the other opinion is.
שמאי Shammai is very strict, even one bone from the skull or
one bone from the backbone. What does the opposite opinion say? Yesterday
we said you can't, maybe the opposite opinion needs both the skull
and the backbone. Even if we conclude that the opposite opinion is
skull or backbone, you can't figure out whether how much of a
quantity of bones the other side would say suffices. Would they agree
to שמאי Shammai that you have to treat the skull and backbone
weightier and therefore say it's not a half קב kav but a
quarter of a קב? kav? Or would they just disagree and say
you treat it like רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין rov
binyan and it's a half of a קב? kav? So we have
no way of inferring the other opinion. So this question remains unanswered,
which is when you don't have the entire skull and backbone and
you just have a quantity from them, whether for the טומאה tuma
of a נזיר, Nazir, do you need the standard half קב kav
or because the skull and backbone is weightier even a quarter קב
kav would be enough.
Know that from one position in a מחלוקת machloket you can't infer
how wide the מחלוקת machloket is.
Exactly, exactly. Exactly, exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has another question. אמר רבי אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Eliezer*, not another question,
a statement. זקנים הראשונים *Zekeinim ha-rishonim*, the original elders, מקצתן היו אומרים
*miktzatan hayu omerim*. So now we're going to get a little background
and a little history about this whole division here: quarter of a
קב kav? *kab* and a half קב kav *kab*, because you have
to admit, it's pretty strange, right? That you double the שיעור shiur
*shiur* for נזיר מגלח nazir megaleach *Nazir megalei'ach*. And if that was
a rule across the board, fine, that's the rule. But why is
it specifically in this case about the bone and the case about
the blood that you double the שיעור shiur *shiur* for the נזיר
Nazir *Nazir* from the amount that causes טומאת אהל tum'as ohel. *tumat
ohel*? So אמר רבי אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Eliezer*, זקנים הראשונים *Zekeinim ha-rishonim*,
the early elders, מקצתן היו אומרים *miktzatan hayu omerim*, חצי קב עצמות
chatzi kav atzamos וחצי לוג דם vechatzi log dam, לכל *chatzi kab
atzamot ve-chatzi log dam le-kol*. They would they originally said that for
for all purposes, טומאה tumah *tuma*, תרומה Trumah *teruma*, נזיר Nazir *Nazir*,
פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, קדשים Kodshim, *kodashim*, any הלכות *halachot*, the amount you
need for טומאת אהל ohel, *tumat ohel* is a half of a
קב kav, *kab* of bones and a half of a לוג *log*
of blood, meaning this was their general שיעור shiur *shiur* for all
things. Makes sense? Okay, yeah, like have one שיעור shiur *shiur*, okay.
לכל *Le-kol*, for all things. ורובע עצמות ורביעית דם לא lo, לכל
*Ve-rova atzamot ve-revi'it dam lo le-kol*.
And the quarter of a of a קב kav, *kab* of bones
and the quarter of a לוג *log* of blood was not
for nothing, okay? That wasn't a שיעור shiur *shiur*. ומקצתן היו אומרים
*U-miktzatan hayu omerim*, and another group of the elders said, אף רובע
עצמות rova atzamot? ורביעית דם לכל *Af rova atzamot ve-revi'it dam le-kol*.
No, I'm sorry, the quarter of the of the קב *kab* of
bones and the quarter of the לוג *log* of blood, that that's
for everything. They weren't distinguishing between נזיר Nazir, *Nazir* and other things.
They were there's a major debate: half of a קב *kab* or
a quarter of a קב *kab*, half of a לוג *log* or
a quarter of a לוג *log*. So much for the opinion that
all שיעורים shiurim הם הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai *shiurim hem
halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai*, right? Because alright. So anyway, so well well, that's
going to be the conclusion. But they were very clearly saying that
we don't distinguish between the cases. בית דין של אחריהם אמרו *Beit
din shel achareihem amru*, but the final בית דין *beit din* said,
חצי קב עצמות chatzi kav atzamos וחצי לוג דם לכל *chatzi kab
atzamot ve-chatzi log dam le-kol*, was רובע עצמות ורביעית דם לתרומה וקדשים
אבל לא lo, לנזיר ועושה פסח *rova atzamot ve-revi'it dam le-teruma ve-kodashim
aval lo le-Nazir ve-oseh Pesach*. So a half of a קב *kab*
of bones and a half of a לוג *log* of blood would
be for everybody, because obviously if you have twice the שיעור shiur
*shiur*, that's enough for all purposes of טומאה tuma. *tuma*. So it's
a little misleading statement, and you really have to have it in
juxtaposition with the next statement. If you have a half, if you
have double the שיעור shiur, *shiur* then of course for all purposes
everybody is טמא tamei, *tamei*. But if you only have the quarter
of the of the קב עצמות kav atzamot, *kab atzamot* and the
quarter of the לוג *log* of blood, that's only טומאה tumah *tuma*
for תרומה Trumah *teruma* and קדשים Kodshim. *kodashim*, okay? So for context
now you're considered טמא tamei מת met, *tamei meit* for eating תרומה
Trumah *teruma* and קדשים Kodshim *kodashim*, but not for if you're a
נזיר Nazir *Nazir*, you wouldn't have to shave and you know bring
the קרבנות *korbanot* and so on. You'd be טמא *tamei*, you'd have
to become טהור tahor. *tahor*, but it would not destroy your נזירות
*nezirut* and the whole thing. And if you're bringing a קרבן פסח
korban Pesach. *korban Pesach*, that's also fascinating, which doesn't mean you can
enter into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, but it means
the ability to bring a קרבן korban פסח *korban Pesach* for somebody
who is in a state of טומאה tumah *tuma*. Now does that
mean that we would actually let that person eat the קרבן פסח
*korban Pesach*? It's not sort of spelled out here. So this is
very interesting. Right now, if you were to be told that there's
this difference: for תרומה Trumah *teruma* and קדשים Kodshim *kodashim* we're going
to you're considered טמא *tamei*, but for פסח *Pesach* and נזיר Nazir
*Nazir* you're not going to reverse and bring another קרבן *korban* or
you're not going to not be able to bring a קרבן פסח
*korban Pesach*, etc. The most natural thing to say in this case
would have been דאורייתא *de-oraita* and דרבנן derabanan? *de-rabbanan*, right? That that
דאורייתא *de-oraita* it's a half of a קב *kab*, מדרבנן mi'd'Rabanan *mi-de-rabbanan*
we're going to be strict with a רביעית revi'is *revi'it*,
but we're not going to hold by that דרבנן derabanan? *de-rabbanan* when
there are very like weighty consequences of a קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*
or when it's going to force you to bring a קרבן *korban*
as a נזיר Nazir *Nazir* that you're not really obligated to bring,
right? Because if you're not really דאורייתא טמא *de-oraita tamei*. So the
most natural thing here to be to say would be that this
is the real שיעור shiur *shiur*, and we go by this as
a strictness מדרבנן mi'd'Rabanan. *mi-de-rabbanan*, but we don't hold by it, you
know, under certain circumstances. And I want to remind you that we
said something very similar to that earlier when we were dealing with
what was the case earlier we were dealing with?
Hold on, let me just find it. It was something else that
we made the exception for the עושה פסח Oseh Pesach, *oseh Pesach*.
It was not טומאת התהום *tumat ha-tehom*, one minute.
Yeah. Wait, no, hold on.
Let me
check this.
Anybody remembering this?
Oh, it was the טומאת חיבורין *tumat chiburin*. It was on דף
מב עמוד ב *daf mem-bet amud bet*. If you remember the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said, אמר רב ינאי *Amar Rav Yannai*, I'm just I'll
just read to you: לא אמרו טומאה בחיבורין tumah bechiburin *Lo amru
tuma be-chiburin*—remember the whole thing about touching a מת met. *meit* and
somebody touching the person touching the
מת met *meit*—לא אמרו טומאה tumah בחיבורין אלא לתרומה וקדשים *lo amru
tuma be-chiburin ela le-teruma ve-kodashim*. אבל לנזיר ולעושה פסח לא *Aval le-Nazir
u-le-oseh Pesach lo*. Sounds familiar, right? A line between תרומה Trumah *teruma*,
קדשים Kodshim *kodashim*, נזיר Nazir *Nazir*, and עושה פסח Oseh Pesach *oseh
Pesach*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now listen to what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says: ואי אמרת דאורייתא, מאי שנא *Ve-i amrat de-oraita, mai
shena*? than the other. So this distinction would suggest that the דאורייתא
שיעור is this, and that's why that's what we hold by for
a נזיר Nazir and a פסח. עושה פסח, Oseh Pesach we're not
going to make the נזיר Nazir bring a קרבן that he's not
really obligated to bring. We're not going to prevent the guy from
bringing a קרבן פסח. But מדרבנן under general purposes, we'll say even
half that amount. Nevertheless, that's not the way the גמרא Gemara, concludes.
The גמרא Gemara concludes that these, this distinction is a basically הלכה
למשה מסיני halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai distinction, that there really are two different
שיעורים shiurim for these two different categories. And let's take a look.
גמרא Gemara says—wait, let's read the end. Let's read the end. You
don't know that yet. You could have said, if you had stopped
here, I would have said it's a מדרבנן. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. מכדי, michti, says the גמרא, Gemara אין אחרונה
שלישית מכרעת. ain achrona shlishis machra'as. The third opinion does not qualify
as a compromise position, as a deciding opinion. Now what does it
mean? So normally, we have an inclination to assume that if you've
got a third opinion which basically is a compromise or a midpoint
between the other two, that we might be מכריע machria according to
that, we would decide the הלכה Halacha according to that. But not
if it's a third opinion that's not really, that's just a third
opinion, that's not really a compromise position. Okay, and now here—what? So
how do you know—no, no, no, I mean, meaning if you can't
conceptualize it as a compromise between the two, okay, which is like—what?
But what makes that one the third one?
Well, because you have two extremes and you have one in the
middle. So the question is when you have a position that's in
the middle of the two extremes, is it conceptualized as a compromise
or is it conceptualized as a third opinion? When you think of
it as a compromise, then we more are inclined to פסקן pasken
like it. If you think of a third opinion, then there are
three equal opinions. Here we know we פסקן pasken like it. Here
right, our משנה mishna says חצי קב chatzi kav for נזיר, Nazir
and we have other משניות mishnayos in אהלות Ohalos that tell us
a רביעית קב, revi'is a kav, and we've quoted some of them,
רביעית revi'is, for a normal טומאת מת. tumas meis. So we know
we פסקן pasken this third opinion, but what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is this isn't a compromise position. Now how do you know
it's not a compromise? It sounds like a compromise to me. We
apply your הלכה Halacha some of the time and your הלכה Halacha
some of the time. Right? So what the מפרשים meforshim say is,
I'm trying to think of an example where something sounds like a
compromise but it isn't.
I should have come up with a good example before—anyway, but you
can imagine how some type of a cases is not really midpoint,
it's just, it has the appearance of being a compromise but it's
really nothing like that.
The way the מפרשים meforshim say here why it's not conceptualized as
a compromise is because if originally the first position said this is
the שיעור for נזיר Nazir and עושה פסח Oseh Pesach and תרומה
Trumah and קדשים, Kodshim. and the other one said no, this is
the שיעור for נזיר עושה פסח—it Nazir Oseh Pesach doesn't matter whether
it's נזיר עושה פסח Nazir Oseh Pesach or תרומה Trumah and קדשים.
Kodshim And the third opinion said no, no, no, for נזיר nazir
and עושה פסח Oseh Pesach it's this, for תרומה Trumah and קדשים
Kodshim it's that, then it would have—then that's building on the other
two because the other two acknowledge that there is a category difference
between those two and it's just saying that—that even though
conceptually נזיר nazir. עושה פסח Oseh Pesach is one category and תרומה
and קדשים kadashim. in another, I'm not making a distinction between them.
But you're acknowledging that there are those two categories. If you were
to say it's a חצי קב chatzi kav for everything, but you
didn't just say the words everything, you said it's a חצי קב
chatzi kav whether it's נזיר nazir and עושה פסח Oseh Pesach or
whether it's תרומה and קדשים it's a חצי קב. chatzi kav. And
the other over there said it's a רביעית הקב revi'is hakav whether
it's נזיר nazir and עושה פסח Oseh Pesach whether it's תרומה or
קדשים. And I said no, no, no, for נזיר nazir עושה פסח
it's this, for תרומה and קדשים it's that. That would be seen
as a הכרעה hachra'ah because the two of you have acknowledged that
conceptually there would be a reason to distinguish between the two, even
though you deny that that distinction holds in this case. You see?
Right. So but if you basically said I don't understand where anybody
could distinguish between anything, all of טומאה tumah is the same, so
my idea of introducing this distinction of תרומה and קדשים on the
one hand and נזיר nazir and עושה פסח on the other is
not a הכרעה. hachra'ah. It's me introducing a new type of a
concept that the two of you don't even acknowledge is a legitimate
distinction. Okay, so that's why it's considered to be a third opinion
and not a sort of הכרעה hachra'ah type of an opinion. I
mean here,
here would be an example, here would be an example. Okay, the
husband wants to live in New York, the wife wants to move
in LA. So let's be מכריע machria and say that they're going
to live in Ohio. Okay. That's not a הכרעה, hachra'ah, right? So
what? Because it's a בריה בפני עצמה? birya bifnei atzma? Right.
So that's a בריה בפני עצמה birya bifnei atzma would be like
a not a הכרעה hachra'ah position, right. So sometimes even though it
looks like it's midpoint, it's not a הכרעה hachra'ah because it's not
part of the same universe as the other two were talking about.
Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
That would have to be Kansas City.
Right.
That just shows how good my geography is. Okay, right. If it
was Kansas City, that would be a הכרעה, hachra'ah, yes.
So in spite of all this, you know, you're not going to
get the record, you're not going to get this, you're not going
to get that, and you know, maybe you need all the—at the
end of the day, if a נזיר nazir said, you know, I
walked through a graveyard, I would have said you're— Right, oh
well, you walk over and you exhume all the bodies and like,
you know, see if there really was a skull and there really,
you know, or if it disintegrated and whatever. Well, okay, that's a
good question. What do you do in case of a ספק? safek?
You know, that he walked over a grave and you know, what
assumptions do we make? I mean, assume we would make an assumption
that all the bones are there. You know, but that's a good
question. What do you do in a case of a ספק? safek?
But let's not worry about that right now. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara can conclude.
That has to be very practical, you know what I mean? More
so than like...
I know, but I mean we're going to assume all the bones
are there, I think. But you're right. I mean after a long
enough time, how do you know, maybe even the bones just disintegrate.
All right. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. והא אין
הכרעה שלישית מכרעת, Veha ein hachra'ah shelishit machra'at, okay,
which means this is not really a compromise position. It's a third
position. So where do where do they get off coming and coming
up with this third position? So the גמרא Gemara says, where are
you? Do you have והא veha in there? No, I'm not, I'm
just doing it from memory. I'm looking for it. I'm looking for
it. I'm looking for it. Okay, מכדי אין הכרעה שלישית מכרעת, Michdi
ein hachra'ah shelishit machra'at, אמר רבי יעקב בר אידי, Amar Rabbi Yaakov
bar Idi, מפי שמועה אמרו. Mipi shemuah amru. No,
they're not saying this as on their own sort their own way
of compromising. They have this as a tradition. מפי חגי זכריה ומלאכי
Mipi Chagai Zechariah uMalachi going all the way back to the beginning
of the second בית המקדש. Why it attributes it specifically to those
נביאים nevi'im I don't know. Very... and רש"י... Rashi... I don't know,
and they didn't have the same tradition. Okay, but basically, you know,
so I sort of framed it as this isn't a compromise, so
why do we פסקן pasken this way? That's the way תוספות Tosafot
frames it. You could have framed it as how do you get
up, how do you come on your own making a third position,
right? The שיעורים shiurim, have to have a tradition behind them. You
can't just say, oh, I'm going to make a compromise in הלכות
שיעורים. hilchot shiurim. There has to be some tradition behind it. And
the answer is no, we do have a tradition, their tradition actually
goes way back to distinguish between these two. Why it's attributed דווקא
davka to חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chagai Zechariah uMalachi I don't know. Again,
and it's also interesting that the most natural thing to be to
would to be to would've said, which גמרא Gemara said before by
טומאה tumah, בחיבורין was דאורייתא דרבנן, de'oraita derabanan, here it actually claims
that there's a... that actually for the עיקר הלכה ikar halachah is
a distinction between these two categories.
Yes, Rambam says הלכה למשה מסיני halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai. and says מפי
שמועה. mipi shemuah.
Yes, it's not clear that מפי שמועה mipi shemuah is the same
as הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai. מפי שמועה Mipi shemuah could
just mean that it's a tradition that goes all the way back
where they got it from, you know, like for example, the נצי"ב
Netziv says when the גמרא Gemara says הלכה, halachah, often רש"י Rashi
says it means הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai. And the נצי"ב
Netziv says what it really means is is that it goes... it's
an ancient tradition that goes way way back and we forgot the
original reason why it was decided upon. So it could be a
very long tradition, but it's not the same as the claim of
הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai?
So how would you say that?
Well, how would you know when if הלכה למשה מסיני?
halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
Oh, when it says הלכה halachah, למשה מסיני. But when it says
it's הלכה, halachah. then it just means like this... this long tradition,
but we're not claiming that it's... so... yeah...
you don't need the authority of scriptural interpretation because it's prior to
that. It's on the authority of נביאים, nevi'im, right? So...
well, no, but that's the whole question about the role of נביאים
nevi'im in terms of they don't get a set... a particular say
in הלכה. halacha So it's really... right, although it's funny though because
it's... it seems to be attributing it somewhat because of their status
of נביאים. nevi'im. It's an... it's a question, right, exactly what the...
yeah.
And if this is just from חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Chagai Zechariah uMalachi,
wouldn't that make it דרבנן? derabanan. Just a very old דרבנן?
No, so that's the point. It's a tradition that goes back to
them and where did they get the tradition from? So is the
implication they got it through נבואה, nevuah, which raises whole questions of
נבואה nevuah in the הלכתי halachic process, okay, or is the implication
that they got it because they were אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah and they were part of the chain of tradition, right, so
it's not all spelled out.
Yeah. And from חגי זכריה ומלאכי, Chagai Zechariah uMalachi, we know instituted
גזירות. gezeirot.
Right, but I don't think the suggestion is not that it's דרבנן.
Okay, let's take a look at the next slice. על אלו נזיר
מגלח. Al elu nazir megaleach.
So those were all of the things that cause טומאת אוהל, tumat
ohel, okay, the the skull, the backbone, the quantity of bones, the
blood, the etc. so on. כזית Kezayit of flesh. All those things
cause טומאת אוהל tumat ohel and all of those things is a
נזיר Nazir shaves his head of. And as we've said, the issue
about the quantity of the bones and the blood is double the
size for נזיר מגלח nazir megaleach than normal
טומאת אוהל, tumat ohel, okay. על אלו דרישו למעוטי Al elu derishu
lema'utei עצם כשעורה. etzem keshe'orah. So when it says these, it's coming
to say yes, because there's one thing that causes טומאת מת tumat
meit that is not in that list because it's not טומאת אוהל,
tumat ohel, which is a piece of bone the size of a
barley bean... of a barley grain. דעל מגע ועל משא אין ועל
אהל לא, De'al maga ve-al masa in ve-al ohel lo, that for
touching and carrying yes, but for being an אוהל ohel over it
or under the same אוהל ohel no. So even though that's really
explicit in the משנה, Mishnah, because right after this list the משנה
Mishnah says עצם כשעורה etzem keshe'orah for touching and
carrying, okay, the גמרא Gemara. still... it's actually interesting. This גמרא Gemara?
for once is sort of saying it's taking a type of a
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael approach of דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם dibra
Torah kilschon bnei adam to the משנה. Mishnah. You know, it's pretty
funny when the גמרא Gemara sort of takes an approach like the
משנה Mishnah like it takes to the פסוקים, pesukim, like every single
extra word you have to דרשן. darshan. But here it's saying no,
the משנה's Mishnah like פשט. peshat. It first gives you a first
list which is about טומאת אוהל tumat ohel and says these a
נזיר. Because it's going to exclude what it's going to mention in
the next list, which is the little piece of bone that's only
for touching and not for being in the אוהל. ohel. ואלו דסיפא
למיעוטי אבן הסוכך. ve'eilu deseifa lemi'utei even hasochach. And then the משנה
Mishnah ends with saying ואלו הנזיר מגלח ve'eilu hanazir megaleach
because what it's coming to exclude is the following משנה, Mishnah, which
is going to have a whole series of טומאות tumaos that a
נזיר is not מגלח megaleach for. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah we
dealt with had טומאות tumaos that a נזיר is מגלח megaleach for,
but there were two lists, one that included טומאת אוהל tumas ohel
and one that was not with טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. And so
the ואלו ve'eilu in the first is dividing those two lists, and
the ואלו ve'eilu at the end of the משנה Mishnah is dividing
that משנה Mishnah from the משנה Mishnah we're about to get to,
which are cases that a נזיר does not shave for. And one
of them is this like a stone wall that has an overhanging
stone and an overcropping stone. We'll see about that when we get
to it. A stone wall, we'll see about that. Okay, now וחצי
קב עצמות. vechatzi kav atzamos. Okay, now we're for whatever reason we're
now sort of doubling back
here for וחצי קב עצמות. vechatzi kav atzamos. So וחצי קב עצמות
vechatzi kav atzamos in, רוב עצמות rov atzamos לא, not a רוב
עצמות. rov atzamos. So היכי דמי? heichi dami? אילימא דאית בהן עצמות
כשעורה, eileima de'is ban atzamos keseora, תיפוק ליה משום עצם כשעורה. teipok
lei mishum etzem keseora. So
let's take a look back at the משנה Mishnah and remind ourselves
what the משנה Mishnah is saying here. So the משנה Mishnah is
on
מ"ט
עמוד ב'. mem
tes amud
beis. It's actually funny because the גמרא's Gemara doubling back because the
משנה Mishnah says, if you look at it the first wide line
of מ"ט עמוד ב', mem tes amud beis, it says על שדרה
ועל גולגולת al shidra ve'al gulgoles which we discussed, על אבר מן
המת ועל אבר מן החי שיש עליו בשר כראוי, al ever min
hamet ve'al ever min hachai sheyesh alav basar karaui. וחצי קב עצמות,
vechatzi kav atzamos, וחצי לוג דם, ועל המגע ועל המשא ועל האוהל,
ve'al hamaga ve'al hamasa ve'al ha'ohel, ועל עצם כשעורה, ve'al etzem keseora,
ועל המגע ועל המשא, ve'al hamaga ve'al hamasa, על אלו הנזיר מגלח.
al eilu hanazir megaleach. So jump to the על אלו, al eilu,
but now it's going back to the וחצי קב עצמות vechatzi kav
atzamos which was earlier. It had mostly focused on the שדרה וגולגולת
shidra ve'gulgoles if you remember, most of our discussion had been there
on the שדרה shidra and the גולגולת, gulgoles, and then
so then we jumped to the על אלו al eilu and now
we're doubling back to the וחצי קב עצמות. vechatzi kav atzamos. So
let's take a look back to the גמרא. Gemara וחצי קב עצמות
vechatzi kav atzamos in, רוב עצמות rov atzamos לא, not a רוב
עצמות. rov atzamos. So היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא
דאית בהן עצמות כשעורה eileima de'is ban atzamos keseora if all of
the bones are the size of a barley bean תיפוק ליה משום
עצם כשעורה. teipok lei mishum etzem keseora. Why do you need a
half-קב? Even one tiny little bone is enough to cause
טומאה. tumah אלא דאיקמח חמוכי. ela de'ikmach chamuchei. It must be that
they've been turned into like flour, they've been so pulverized that they're
like dust and therefore there's not even an עצם כשעורה etzem keseora
and nevertheless a חצי קב עצמות chatzi kav atzamos would be enough.
But the question is what's bothering the גמרא? Gemara One sentence ago
and just פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah is we're talking about
טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. So טומאת אוהל tumas ohel it doesn't matter
that it's the size of a barley grain, you need a חצי
קב chatzi kav for טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. So let's take a
look at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says צריך עיון. tzarich iyun. מאי
קא פריך? mai ka parich? What's it asking?
דלעניין אוהל איירינן dele'inyan ohel airinan ועצם כשעורה לא מטמא באוהל. ve'etzem
keseora lo metamei be'ohel. What's going on?
So תוספות Tosafos goes through a whole answer about that somehow the
גמרא Gemara understands, it's a very complicated answer, but he basically
says that somehow the גמרא Gemara. understands that this case is meant
to exclude that there's scenarios that are less than a חצי קב
עצמות chatzi kav atzamos. that are not just not מטמא באוהל metamei
be'ohel but not מטמא metamei at all. So the גמרא Gemara for
whatever reason assumes that that's implied, that there are some scenarios that
it's not מטמא metamei at all. What's the case that it's not
מטמא metamei at all? Less than a חצי קב chatzi kav when
it's turned totally into
dust, when it's turned to dust.
All right, and so less than a חצי קב chatzi kav עצמות
would not be מטמא באוהל metamei be'ohel no matter how big the
bones are, but a scenario where it would be מטמא באוהל metamei
be'ohel but not be מטמא metamei if it was less than that
would be if it was all dust-like. That would not prevent it
from being מטמא באוהל metamei be'ohel even if it was dust-like, but
nevertheless less than a חצי קב chatzi kav, in that scenario would
not be מטמא metamei at all. Okay, so that's the חצי קב
chatzi kav, עצמות. Now על אבר מן המת ועל אבר מן החי.
al ever min hamet ve'al ever min hachai It's very bizarre, it's
going in like a reverse order reading this משנה. Mishnah. I can't
explain why. על אבר מן המת ועל אבר מן החי al ever
min hamet ve'al ever min hachai. שיש עליו בשר כראוי. sheyesh alav
basar karaui, So now we're dealing, we dealt with the bones, we
dealt with
רוב מניין rov minyan and רוב בניין rov binyan before, and we
dealt with the skull and the backbone, and now we're dealing with
the אבר, ever, a limb from a corpse or a limb from
a live person that has enough בשר כראוי. basar ka-ra’uy, And כראוי
karaui. we said means as much as it could heal if it
was attached to a live person. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אבר שאין עליו בשר כראוי מאי? eiver she-ein alav basar k'raui
mai? What if there is not enough flesh on it? Now the
answer is, what do you mean what's not enough flesh on it?
Obviously it's not מטמא באהל. metamei b'ohel. So the question is really
the following. What if there is not enough flesh on it and
it's not מטמא באהל, metamei b'ohel, would it still be מטמא במגע?
metamei b'maga? Okay, let's say you have a limb, a finger or
let's say that doesn't have enough flesh on it and it's not
מטמא באהל, metamei b'ohel, would it be מטמא metamei if you touched
it? Now the problem is going to be that okay, but you're
at least touching bone and bone is עצם כשעורה. etzem k'se'ora. So
the גמרא Gemara. is going to say it's a scenario where even
the bone is less than עצם כשעורה. etzem k'se'ora. Now I can't
figure out what limb
has less than עצם כשעורה etzem k'se'ora of bone and doesn't have
enough flesh and still is considered to be an אבר. eiver.
You know,
I mean are there tiny little bones that are
and it says flesh what? Like if if the bone has decomposed
of
the right?
Oh, to shrink, yeah.
And then there's not even flesh.
Right, exactly. So that's going to be the scenario of the גמרא.
Gemara I don't know, maybe it started as a limb and now
it's whatever it is, the scenario of the גמרא Gemara is because
if it's a limb, it doesn't have flesh so it's not מטמא
באהל, metamei b'ohel, is it still מטמא במגע? metamei b'maga? Does it
still have its weight and significance because it started as a limb,
as an אבר, eiver, even though it's not מטמא באהל? metamei b'ohel?
Okay, and but will it be מטמא במגע? metamei b'maga? But in
order to explain how that's a question, it's going to have to
say that even the bone is less than כשעורה, k'se'ora, which is
going to be just hard to imagine what's the case. But let's
take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. אין עליו בשר כראוי
מאי? ein alav basar k'raui mai? What's the story? רבי יוחנן אמר,
Rabbi Yochanan amar, אין הנזיר מגלח עליהם, ein hanazir megaleach aleihem, nothing,
okay? וריש לקיש אמר, v'Reish Lakish amar, הנזיר מגלח עליהם. hanazir megaleach
aleihem. Yes, he will be, again, assuming that you touched it. That
little point is not stated explicitly, but it'll emerge. Okay, רבי
יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, אין הנזיר מגלח עליהם, ein hanazir megaleach
aleihem, דהקתני ברישא, de-katani b'reisha, אבר מן המת ואבר מן החי שיש
עליהם כזית בשר, eiver min hamet v'eiver min hachai she-yesh aleihem k'zayit
basar, אין, in, אבל אין עליהם לא. aval ein aleihem lo. It's
very clear. It tells you you need these parameters, the implication being
anything less than that, it's not מטמא. metamei. The one thing that
didn't satisfy the first list that still would be נזיר מגלח nazir
megaleach, would be bones, right? If it's not a חצי קב, chatzi
kav you would still מגלח megaleach if you touched it and that
was stated explicitly. So anything else that's not on the list that
doesn't satisfy the שיעורים, shiurim. the נזיר is not מגלח megaleach under
any circumstances. רבי שמעון בן לקיש אמר, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish amar,
מגלח. megaleach. How do you know it? מדלא קתני בסיפא. mi-d'lo katani
b'seifa. Ah, because there are two סיפאs, seifa right? There are two
lists. There's the list
of that's right.
Our משנה, mishna, right?
משנה mishna one said like this, okay? נזיר מגלח, megaleach. and then
it had basically two lists: אהל, ohel okay, and it basically had,
you know, what did it have?
כזית בשר, k'zayit basar,
שדרה, shidra,
גולגולת, gulgollet,
right, חצי
קב, chatzi kav, you know, whatever it had, אבר, eiver, which is
what we're dealing with, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot. And then it
said, and then it had a מגע maga list which basically was
just עצם כשעורה. etzem k'se'ora. Okay, so and by the אבר eiver
it says שיש עליו בשר כראוי, she-yesh alav basar k'raui, שיש עליו
בשר כראוי. she-yesh alav basar k'raui. So comes רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and he says, look, if it's basically it's not on this list,
it's not on this list, okay, so then נזיר isn't מגלח. megaleach
If you were to say that when it's אין עליו בשר כראוי,
ein alav basar k'raui, it's טומאת מגע, tumas maga, it should have
been on this list. It's not on either list, it's not מגלח.
megaleach, Ah, but the next משנה mishna which we're about to get
to on דף נ"ד, daf nun daled, משנה mishna two says the
following is אין הנזיר מגלח, ein hanazir megaleach,
okay? And that list does not give the example of אבר שאין
עליו בשר כראוי. eiver she-ein alav basar k'raui. Let's read that list
for a minute. Turn to
דף נ"ד, daf nun daled, okay, אבל השככות והפרעות ובית הפרס, aval
hash'chachos v'hapraot u'veit hapras, okay, so those are places, those aren't parts
of the body, those are places that you're walking, we won't worry
about that right now, we'll get to that tomorrow. ארץ העמים, eretz
ha-amim, so forget that for a moment. והגולל והדופק, v'hagolel v'hadofek, that's
parts of the like tombstone, parts of the grave. And here's what's
relevant for us, ורביעית דם והאהל ורוב העצמות, v'revi'it dam v'haohel v'rov
ha-atzamot, okay, הכלים הנוגעים במת. ha-keilim ha-nog'im b'met. So here's where אין
הנזיר מגלח. ein hanazir megaleach. So what does a נזיר not מגלח
megaleach for? Okay, so here it said חצי קב chatzi kav and
חצי
לוג, chatzi log, and here it said רביעית לוג, revi'it log, and
what else did it say?
רביעית דם, revi'it dam, that's רביעית לוג דם, revi'it log dam, and
did it say? רביעית דם revi'it dam ורוב העצמות, v'rov ha-atzamot, which
is רביעית הקב, revi'it ha-kav, okay, רביעית הקב. revi'it ha-kav. Okay, so
basically said here it had those counterparts. For that amount he is
מגלח, megaleach. for this amount he isn't. Okay, yes? Okay, now the
others, okay, you could have said I guess you could have said
less than חצי כזית בשר, chatzi k'zayit basar, but you know, less
than שדרה, shidra, but something that's not שדרה, shidra, not גולגולת, gulgollet,
I don't know, it's interesting. It doesn't have counterparts for this, but
maybe the גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming why. Logically there's nothing, there's no meaningful
less than in this case. It doesn't have to mention the less
than here. But the חצי קב, chatzi kav, חצי לוג chatzi log
is a meaningful less, רביעית קב, revi'is kav, רביעית לוג, revi'is log,
which normally has significance. So אבר שיש עליו בשר כראוי, ever she-yesh
alav basar karui, right, does have some meaningful thing that's less. אבר
שאין עליו בשר כראוי. ein alav basar karui. ושיש עליו ve-she-yesh alav
is an implicit like criteria. So what would be when that part
is not met? So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says well it's not
on this list. So if it's not on this list, I'm going
to infer that a נזיר is מגלח megaleach, by touching, not by
אוהל. ohel. Okay? You don't get it?
I mean I get it, but if you have a list, but
yeah it's on a list of things and something that falls in
between why do you automatically assume it goes into this? No.
Well he's assuming that anything that right, so I understand well that's
true, that's always the case of the excluded middle, I agree with
that. But what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is saying is that anything that would have
suggested like that we know that there's a suggested alternative, right, like
a חצי קב chatzi kav, and חצי לוג, chatzi log, the question
is well what about a רביעית קב revi'is kav and a רביעית
לוג? revi'is log? Those are normally significant. So that's mentioned here. So
אבר שיש עליו בשר ever she-yesh alav basar suggests a case of
אבר שאין עליו בשר. ever she-ein alav basar. And he is saying
that if it's not on the list of אינו נזיר, eino Nazir,
I'm going to assume יש. yesh. Now of course it's funny because
if it's יש, yesh, it's not on this list either and it
should have been on here. I understand. I mean רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan position seems much stronger. This says יש, yesh, it's a very
complete list, okay, and if some scenario doesn't belong here and it
belongs here, it should have been said. What ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
would probably say is that the שיש עליו she-yesh alav suggests שאין
עליו she-ein alav is on the second list. I don't know why.
Okay. But anyway that's their debate. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says hey,
it's not on this list, it's טהור. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says
no, it's not on this list, it's טמא, it's מגלח. megaleach. Okay?
So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ריש לקיש
אומר מגלח משום לא תני בסיפא. Resh Lakish omer megaleach mishum lo
tana b'seifa. רבי יוחנן אמר לך כל היכא דמשמע מכללה לא תני
בסיפא. Rabbi Yochanan amar lach kol heicha d'mashma miklala lo tana b'seifa.
It doesn't have to tell you things in the סיפא seifa that
are implicit in the כללא. klala. The first משנה Mishna says יש,
yesh, it's implicit if it's not on this list the answer is
no, we don't have to say it again in the second משנה.
Mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, וחצי קב עצמות דמשמע
חצי קב עצמות אין רובע עצמות לא? v'chatzi kav atzamot d'mashma chatzi
kav atzamot in rova atzamot lo? And
that's not true. Some things are implicit and they're mentioned in the
second משנה. Mishna. It says a half of a קב yes, implying
less than a half of a קב, meaning a quarter of a
קב, would not be מגלח, וקתני בסיפא v'katani b'seifa רובע עצמות? And
it's mentioned in the second משנה. Mishna. So you see the second
משנה Mishna goes out of its way to say things even if
they're implicit in the first.
The גמרא Gemara says בסיפא רובע עצמות? b'seifa rova atzamot? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, התם אי לאו רובע עצמות, hasam ee lav
rova atzamot, if it had not said it in the סיפא, seifa,
הוה אמינא אפילו אמגע ואמשא לא. hava amina afilu amaga ve-amasa lo.
להכי
אצטריך למתני רובע עצמות
דעל אהילה הוא דאינו נזיר מגלח. l'hachi itztrich l'misni rova atzamot d'al
ahila hu d'eino nazir megaleach.
He says look, the reason it said it here is because if
you remember that line in the משנה, Mishna, it was a funny
construction, that משנה Mishna on דף נ"ד daf nun daled said, רביעית
דם ואוהל ורובע עצמות. revi'is dam v'ohel v'rova atzamot. What do you
mean ואוהל? v'ohel? It means the אוהל ohel of these. Okay? So
it's רביעית הקב, revi'is hakav, it's
אוהל ohel of the, not of these, of the רביעית הקב. revi'is
hakav. Okay? So what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying is you're
right, it didn't have to say, it really in principle didn't have
to say this. I would have known that if it was less
than a
חצי chatzi קב, it wouldn't be נטמא. nitma. But the only thing
is it wouldn't be מגלח. But the only thing is if it
had not been explicit, you might have thought that less than that
is still טמא through you know
even through מגע maga is not a problem. So therefore it has
to explicitly say it's not a problem through אוהל. ohel. Okay? So
in general it does not have to list things on this list
at all that are implicit, that are not on this list, if
it's not on this list implicitly it's not a problem. But the
reason it said it is because you might have come to the
conclusion half of a קב עצמות, anything less is not a problem
even if you touch it. Okay? But even so but that's not
true, if you touch it it is a problem. So it says
explicitly on this list it's אוהל ohel of the חצי קב, of
the רביעית הקב revi'is hakav that's not a problem. Touching it would
still be a problem. Of course the problem is that we already
said that's in כזית kezayis down here. We already made it explicit
that touching is a problem. Okay, so that might be why the
גמרא Gemara said before, now we're going to understand the גמרא Gemara
earlier, that where it's איקמחי כמחה, ikmachi k'mucha, that it's turned into
sort of dust, okay, which is is that well let's take a
look. Hold on, forget that, I'm going to confuse you. Let's read
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay? So it says like this. ואמשא
לא, להכי אצטריך למתני רובע עצמות דעל אהילה הוא דאינו נזיר מגלח.
ve-amasa lo, l'hachi itztrich
l'misni rova
atzamot d'al ahila hu d'eino nazir megaleach. So then
the גמרא Gemara says like this, one minute, וחצי לוג דם דשמעת
מינה חצי לוג דם אין רביעית דם לא? v'chatzi log dam d'shamas
minei chatzi log dam in revi'is dam lo? Okay? That it says
that a חצי לוג דם chatzi log dam yes, implicitly less not,
וקתני בסיפא רביעית דם? v'katani b'seifa revi'is dam? So how about this?
Like because a רביעית, revi'is? why did it have to say רביעית?
revi'is, חצי לוג דם chatzi log dam anything less is not a
problem. Okay, even touching less is not a problem.
So why did it have to say רביעית לוג? revi'is log? I
already knew that anything less is not a problem.
So the גמרא Gemara
says התם לאפוקי מדברי רבי עקיבא. hasam l'afukei midivrei Rabbi Akiva. That's
as
we just saying, we're repeating רביעית דם revi'is dam because we have
this, you know, sort of this,
very persistent position of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so we want to
sort of re-emphasize it we reject it.
דאמר רבי עקיבא רביעית דם הבא משני מתים מטמא באהל. d'amar Rabbi
Akiva revi'is dam haba mishnei meisim mitamei b'ohel. Okay, it's here the
משני מתים mishnei meisim is not as significant but רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva a big proponent of the רביעית דם revi'is dam position so
we want to underscore that we reject רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So
here we want to underscore that it's only less than that amount
of bones is only not a problem if it's אהל ohel. although
it is really implicit here. It might have to do with why
the גמרא Gemara before gave a scenario of turning to dust, we
can see if that sort of fits into this. Anyway, but that's
why we said this and here we said it because of this
persistent position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But fundamentally רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is saying is you don't really have to repeat things here
that are already implicitly rejected here. Okay, so that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is that between these two lists, there's two
different sort of organizational categories. One is like quantity, חצי and רביעית,
right? And the other is modality, מגע maga or אהל. ohel So
it's like depending upon how you mixed and matched you read the
implication of the two lists differently, right? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
reading it one way but you don't have to read it that
way.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this. Okay, so
basically look, each one of them has to deal with a problem.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has to deal with the problem which is
if anything not on this list is not a problem, why did
it repeat these two? So he says, yeah, whatever, repeated them just
to clarify. Was this already implicit from here? Okay fine, it doesn't
hurt to repeat that. Was רביעית לוג revi'is log already implicit from
here? Yeah, but there's a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position, it doesn't
hurt to re-emphasize that. So we mentioned these two but basically if
it's not on this list it's not a problem. And ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says, no,
it's got to be on this list to not be a problem.
You know so
why was it put on this list down here? Who knows? But
he basically says, I'm starting from this list, if it's not on
this list it is a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא says
like this. האי אבר מן המת היכי
דמי?
hai eiver min
hameis heichi dami?
What's the case? אי דאית ביה עצם כשעורה, ei d'is bei etzem
k'seora, if it's got enough bone the size of a barley bean,
what are we talking about touching because we know אהל ohel isn't
a problem? מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן? mai tama d'Rabbi Yochanan? Why is
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying that it's not an issue? אי דלית
ביה עצם כשעורה, ei d'lais bei etzem k'seora, if it doesn't have
that amount of bone, מאי טעמא דריש לקיש? mai tama d'Reish Lakish?
Why is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish saying it is a problem? So
clearly it seems that ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, let's take a look.
So אמר לך ריש לקיש, amar lach Reish Lakish, so ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish could tell you לעולם דלית ביה עצם כשעורה, l'olam d'lais
bei etzem k'seora, it does not have that amount of a bone.
ואפילו הכי רחמנא רבייה, v'afilu hachi Rachmana rabyei, but it's an אבר.
eiver. So since it's a whole אבר, eiver, that's the תורה Torah
is including it. An אבר eiver with its flesh is מטמא באהל,
mitamei b'ohel, without flesh is מטמא במגע mitamei b'maga as an אבר,
eiver, not as a bone. Now again, I cannot figure out what
אבר eiver he's talking about that is conceptually an אבר eiver and
not a bone and that is smaller than the size of a
barley bean. So I don't know what the scenario is.
It has to be עצם דוקא, etzem davka, in other words it
couldn't be a ropey cartilage into this for example, that would give
you something...
I don't know. I mean, I don't imagine what's the smallest bone
in the body anyway.
Ear, inner ear?
Yeah, smaller than a barley bean? What? I never
took
biology.
Okay. Earbone? Earbone? All right. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא.
Braisah. Now we're going to see this idea of an אבר eiver
where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish gets it. He actually has a ברייתא.
Braisah. Now we're going to see that even though clearly רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is a much more פשט pshat reader of the משנה,
Mishna, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish actually has some מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha
that support him. So let's take a look. דתניא, d'tanya, וכל אשר
יגע על פני השדה
ובחלל חרב או במת או בעצם אדם או בקבר.
v'chol asher yiga al pnei hasadeh
u'v'chalal cherev o v'meis o v'etzem adam o v'kaver. So that's okay,
so that's one פסוק. pasuk. Okay, anything you touch על פני השדה.
al pnei hasadeh.
So let's take a look. ובחלל חרב או במת על פני השדה
זה המאהיל. u'v'chalal cherev o v'meis al pnei hasadeh zeh hamahil. So
it's funny you say על פני השדה al pnei hasadeh out in
the open field you would have thought that it somehow meant that
you're no tent is over you, but the גמרא somehow understands it
says וכל אשר יגע על פני השדה. v'chol asher yiga al pnei
hasadeh. But somehow the דרשה drasha is that you're like I don't
know where it gets it from the language of the פסוק, pasuk,
but somehow the דרשה drasha is that you're being an אהל ohel.
over these things and that's to interpret this פסוק pasuk to be
talking about טומאת אהל. ohel. Okay, so let's take a look. Let
me see if תוספות Tosafos helps to explain. על פני, al pnei,
על פני.
al pnei.
Yeah, what does על פני al pnei mean? על פני al pnei
means that somehow you it's you're on top of it.
What? It's extra. Because it says וכל אשר יגע. v'chol asher yiga.
But if anything על פני השדה al pnei hasadeh suggests that you're
not מאהיל mahil over it, right?
Hold on, let me just see if תוספות Tosafos says anything about
this.
Yeah, תוספות Tosafot just says it's superfluous, it could have said כל
אשר יגע. kol asher yiga. Okay, so we're reading this פסוק pasuk
to be about אהל. ohel What? I know. Okay, I don't know.
Yeah, okay. בחלל, be-chalal, so we're talking about על פני השדה, al
pnei hasadeh, זה המאהיל. zeh ha-me'ahil. So number one we're talking about,
we're going to learn from this things that are מטמא באוהל. metamei
be-ohel. על פני, al pnei, על פני, al pnei, okay,
המאהיל על פני המת, ha-me'ahil al pnei hamet, that you are אוהל
ohel on top of, you're facing the מת, met, but you're not
touching it. You're just like suspended above the מת. met. So somehow
from the פני pnei we're getting it. Now, so these are things
that are מטמא באוהל. metamei be-ohel. בחלל, be-chalal, זה אבר מן החי.
zeh eiver min hachai. So חלל chalal is somehow understood that even
if again, I'm not exactly sure how we get this from the
meaning of the word, but somehow it's a person that has been
injured but is not actually been slain, so is a limb from
a live person. ויש לו להעלות ארוכה, ve-yesh lo le-haalot arucha, and
it can be, it has enough flesh on it that if it
were attached, it could heal. Okay, so that's the idea of אבר
מן החי. eiver min hachai. חרב, הרי
זה כחלל. cherev harei zeh ke-chalal. Now, so what? So here, let's
actually write out the
פסוק: pasuk: וכל אשר יגע
על
פני השדה.
ve-chol asher yiga al
pnei hasadeh. So that we just know we're talking about
אוהל, ohel, okay? בחלל חרב או במת
או בעצם
אדם או בקבר.
be-chalal cherev o ve-met o ve-etzem
adam o ve-kever. Okay, so what do we learn out from each
one of these? So
בחלל be-chalal
we somehow learn out אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai.
חרב cherev, we say is חרב הרי הוא כחלל.
cherev harei
hu ke-chalal. What does that mean? That's a very important הלכה halacha
which we're going to get to tomorrow, which means חלל חרב, חרב
כחלל, chalal cherev, cherev ke-chalal, which means that certain כלים, keilim, particularly
metal כלים, keilim, that touch a dead body or that are in
the same אוהל ohel as a dead body, have the same טומאה
tumah as the dead body itself, are considered an אבי אבות הטומאה,
avi avot ha-tumah, not an אב הטומאה. av ha-tumah. Okay, so חרב
הרי הוא כחלל. cherev harei hu ke-chalal. So כלים keilim that touch
the מת met, or are in the same אוהל, ohel, particularly if
they're metal כלים, keilim, we'll talk about this tomorrow. Anyway, they have,
they're an אבי אבות הטומאה, avi avot ha-tumah, they're equal to the
טומאה tumah of a מת, met. not of somebody who touched the
מת. met. That's what you get from חרב. cherev Okay, חרב cherev.
הרי זה
כחלל. harei zeh ke-chalal. או במת, o ve-met, זה אבר הנכלל מן
המת. zeh eiver ha-nechlal min ha-met. So בחלל be-chalal was that the
thing itself somehow is a חלל, chalal, the limb itself is the
dead thing. That's when it's a limb from the חי chai and
only the limb is the dead thing. במת be-met is when it's
an אבר מן המת. eiver min ha-met.
Right?
Okay. So that's the limb is from, that not that the limb
is, that the whole body is a מת, met. not just that
the limb is a מת. meit That's במת. be-met. או
בעצם אדם, o ve-etzem adam, זה רוב עצמות. zeh rov atzamot. Okay,
now עצם etzem sounds like one bone. Of course, we've been saying
that טומאת אוהל tumat ohel has to be a significant amount. So
maybe it's the עצם אדם, etzem adam, okay, it's עצם etzem that
represents the entire person, that is רוב עצמות. rov atzamot.
Okay, so here we have basically pretty much everything on our list.
We have אבר, eiver, we have, I think we don't have the
blood yet. We don't have שדרה וגולגולת. shidrah ve-gulgoret. Maybe that would
be a version of עצם אדם. etzem adam. And we don't have
כזית בשר. ke-zayit basar. Okay, so we don't have really everything yet.
Anyway, okay. או בקבר, o ve-kever, זה קבר סתום. zeh kever satum.
Now קבר סתום, kever satum, so קבר kever means קבר, kever, okay.
But the חידוש chiddush here is, and this is important, we discussed
this
before, this חידוש chiddush is that if you've got a dead body
in a grave, in a, like in a coffin, okay, without the
הלכה halacha of the קבר, kever, the טומאה tumah would only be
opposite the dead body, okay, not opposite the whole coffin. Not only
that, you could have said that one minute, that if there's a
טפח, tefach, maybe the טומאה tumah just goes up to the top
and gets stopped and doesn't even proceed.
I'm sorry, covered or not covered? Covered.
Yeah, covered. Okay. So what?
I thought we said for like an hour there was...
So that's what this is telling you. It's telling you that if
it is a sealed casket, okay, so it has to be sealed
on all sides, okay, that the entire casket becomes like the מת.
meit So number one, it goes the entire width and you know
width and length of the casket and the fact that it's covered
in an אוהל ohel doesn't matter and the entire thing causes טומאה,
tumah which is why it's a problem flying over cemeteries or walking
on some... Correct. You need an אוהל ohel to stop it, and
the only אוהל ohel you have is here, and this is telling
you that the whole קבר kever is considered to be like the
מת. meit. Yes.
Oh, I was going to say that because it's concealed you don't
know where the body is in the casket. Yeah.
Or is it...
I'm sorry, one more time?
You're saying if it's not sealed?
If it's not sealed then just the body is מטמא. metamei. And
not only is just opposite the body מטמא, metamei, but if there's
a space of a טפח, tefach, it actually would stop the טומאה
tumah from going up.
So I guess logically that doesn't make so much sense because I
mean originally because if it's not sealed then that would seem to
let the טומאה tumah out more easily, right?
Ah, yeah, but
if you bury, look, if you bury a body straight in the
ground, which is what they basically do in Israel, right? Then the
טומאה tumah goes straight up opposite the body, okay? Because there's no
אהל. ohel. If you bury in a coffin, then the טומאה doesn't
stop because there's the הלכה halacha of קבר, kever, and the whole
coffin is like the מת meit and goes straight up. If you
were to, like I don't know why nobody ever suggested doing this,
why don't you just bury a body in a coffin that's not
sealed on all sides, right? There's little holes, yeah, and therefore the
טומאה would stop at the top because it would be an אהל
ohel and it wouldn't go up, you know, but whatever, that was
not the practice.
There are holes? Yes, there are holes in the bottom of a
plain pine ארון מתים. aron meitim. Holes in the bottom.
I don't think it needs to be hermetically sealed. I mean, the
definition of סתום satum I can look up. I mean I think
it might have to be...
if there are holes in the bottom, it's not סתום. satum.
Yeah, no, again, I don't know what סתום satum means. סתום satum
might just mean that there are walls on all sides, it might
not mean that they're like hermetically sealed, okay? How big are the
holes anyway? A טפח? tefach? No.
That's probably for purposes of decomposition or whatever, yeah. I don't think
that would affect this הלכה halacha. of סתום. satum. I can look
up what the שיעור of סתום satum is. Okay, so that's that
הלכה. דאמר מר: de-amar mar:
טומאה בוקעת ועולה בוקעת ויורדת. tumah boka’at ve-olah boka’at ve-yoredet. That the
טומאה bursts up and bursts down. Now you didn't have to say
that, but it's basically pointing out what I just said to you,
which is is that if you've got it in the coffin under
the ground, the טומאה is going to go up opposite the whole
thing. Okay, ואי סבירא דתניא? ve-i sevira de-tanya? That's by אהל. ohel
By אהל ohel. we say אבר מן החי אבר מן המת שיש
עליו בשר כראוי. eiver min ha-chai eiver min ha-meit she-yesh alav basar
ka-ra’uy. Okay, that doesn't prove you what happens if there's not בשר
basar כראוי, karaui but now we've got another פסוק, pasuk, we keep
on getting more and more ahead, we have to stop. Now we've
got another פסוק pasuk that talks about touching. ואילו גבי נגיעה, ve-ilu
gabei negiah, when it comes to touching, אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, תני ותנא ברייתא, teni ve-tana baraita, ועל הנוגע בעצם או בחלל
או במת או בקבר. ve-al ha-nogei’a be-etzem o be-chalal o be-meit o
be-kaver. Okay, so that's another פסוק pasuk which is about נגיעה. negiah.
Here we can... I guess
I'll
say... ועל הנוגע
בעצם או בחלל או
במת או
בקבר.
ve-al ha-nogei’a be-etzem o be-chalal
o be-meit o
be-kaver. Okay, seems like pretty darn similar to the previous one. Okay,
ועל הנוגע בעצם או בחלל או במת... ve-al ha-nogei’a be-etzem o be-chalal
o be-meit... בעצם, be-etzem, זה עצם כשעורה. zeh etzem ki-se’orah. So now
since this is about touching, okay, נגיעה, negiah, this is about touching,
so here we have the other שיעורים. עצם כשעורה. etzem ki-se’orah.
Okay, a small amount of bone for touching. או בחלל. o be-chalal.
So now, what do you do with חלל chalal and מת meis
and קבר? kaver? Okay, because anything... the only thing we've had so
far that's touching
that's not
אהל ohel is עצם כשעורה. etzem ki-se’orah. So what else do we
need this list for other than עצם כשעורה? etzem ki-se’orah? So let's
take a look for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said. בחלל, be-chalal, זה
אבר הנחלה מן החי ואין בו להעלות ארוכה. zeh eiver ha-nichleh min
ha-chai ve-ein bo le-haalot arucha. או במת, o be-meit, זה אבר הנחלה
מן המת. zeh eiver ha-nichleh min ha-meit. Ah, so בחלל, be-chalal, the
same way חלל chalal down here meant אבר מן החי, eiver min
ha-chai, it's also אבר מן החי, eiver min ha-chai, but אין בו
להעלות ארוכה. ein bo le-haalot arucha. This is יש עליו בשר כראוי,
yesh alav basar ka-ra’uy, יש עליו בשר כראוי, yesh alav basar ka-ra’uy,
and this is אין עליו בשר כראוי. ein alav basar ka-ra’uy. Exactly
what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said. אין עליו בשר כראוי. ein alav
basar ka-ra’uy. And the same with מת. אבר מן המת. eiver min
ha-meit. The same way. We have two... so the same way we
have אבר מן החי... eiver min ha-chai... two... a different type of
עצם etzem here and עצם etzem there. By the way, notice the
difference between עצם אדם etzem adam as opposed to עצם. etzem. Right?
עצם אדם etzem adam might mean representing the whole person and that's
just an עצם. etzem. I can't say the same for the חלל,
chalal, but anyway חלל chalal and מת here are two different variations
of the אבר מן החי eiver min ha-chai and אבר מן המת.
eiver min ha-meit. This is אבר מן החי eiver min ha-chai and
אבר מן המת eiver min ha-meit that have enough flesh, and these
are אבר מן החי, eiver min ha-chai, אבר מן המת eiver min
ha-meit that don't have enough flesh, and that's only for נגיעה, negiah,
not for אהל. ohel.
Yeah, one's for אהל and one's for נגיעה.
negiah. Which is what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said.
רמינהי, reminhei, let's just finish it. Okay,
או בקבר, o be-kaver, that's the one one we haven't interpreted. אמר
ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, זה קבר שלפני הדיבור. zeh kever she-lifnei
ha-dibbur. The קבר kever before הר סיני. Har Sinai. So before the...
before the word. So because we're way too far ahead, I'm going
to leave you with that cliffhanger. What the קבר kever before the
word means... sounds very mysterious, but what you should see here is
that while the משנה Mishnah clearly seems to support רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, that if it's not enough flesh it's not a problem at
all, okay, you have the מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha which are explicit
like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that say that אבר מן החי eiver
min ha-chai and אבר מן המת eiver min ha-meit that don't have
enough flesh are still a problem through touch even if not through
אהל.
טומאה goes all the way straight up or?
Yeah, no, straight up opposite it.
And if it's not סתום satum meaning there's no top, then what?
No, where there are no sides. If there's a top and no
sides, right, then the טומאה would stop here and if this and
now if this was
the
cover...
you mean the soil?
No, no the cover, he's in a coffin, it has a cover,
so it's like a roof, it stops it, it doesn't go further
up.
How is it not סתום satum if there's a roof? What's holding
the roof?
It doesn't have sides. I don't know, it's got... what do you
mean, you can make a roof with no sides.
Oh, that's what I didn't get. So you're talking about literally there'd
be no sides, you'd be a platform above and below. Exactly. So
then it would stop within the טפח tefach between the מת and
that covering.
Correct.
Yes,
I think it's like flood plain areas like in the Mississippi Delta.
אורה Orah means
light, and
שעורה se'orah is a grain of barley.
Oh,
interesting, right.
Just like underground you have like two layers of אוהל Ohel offset
from each other. That would probably count as
an אוהל. Ohel.
Right, the crypt that it was in. Yeah, yeah, I mean the
גמרא actually has
places that are underground.
Right, exactly, which is why if this weren't סתום satum it would
go straight up. Yeah, exactly.
Question about the שיעור of the... the halachic שיעור of a barley.
Is it an actual barley grain?
Yeah, what do you mean?
So we're using barley grain,
but a lot of people say the כזית kezayit is not really
כזית.
kezayit. I don't know, I haven't looked it up before.
And barley grains vary in
size.
I actually,
one of the reasons on my smartphone I actually looked up the
smallest bone in the human body is about three millimeters long, it's
in the
ear.
Right.
Barley grains raw harvested with the hull are about twice that long
or longer, actually more than twice that long. If you take out
the hull they're smaller. But the pearl barley we buy in the
supermarket has been highly polished and is much smaller. So what is
the שיעור, what is the halachic שיעור that we use?
I don't know, but nobody has explored it too much because it's
only relevant for
טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah which we don't do.
כהנים Kohanim do, but I don't have כהנים Kohanim ask me שאלות
shylas on this little piece of
bone. Most of the question would be בדיעבד b'di'eved I accidentally touched
it and then what's the נפקא מינה, nafka mina, right, you know,
for כהן Kohen it's only a... you never have a בדיעבד b'di'eved
question if they're not about these קדשים.
Right.
How's it going? How was your vacation? Good, good.
Hello, hello,
בוקר טוב. boker tov. It's five. Oh no, oh my gosh, okay,
I forgot the...
I'll cut it.